{"tossups": [{"question": "After Catholics were persecuted in this kingdom, Louis Tromelin led an invasion force. Grover Cleveland was told that the US did not interfere in a rebellion in this kingdom in the Morgan Report. After the overthrow of this kingdom, Lorrin Thurston refused to become president, leading to Sanford Dole\u2019s leadership. This Kingdom had the \u201cBayonet Constitution\u201d imposed on Queen Liliuokalani. For the point, name this Pacific island kingdom that followed Alaska to become the 50th US state.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Hawai\u2019i</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This denomination\u2019s founder studied under Phineas Quimby, but later disavowed his \u201cNew Thought\u201dmovement. \u201cAbsent treatment\u201d is practiced by members of this faith, which distributes works like<em> Pulpit</em> <em>and Press</em> and<em> Manual of the Mother Church</em> in its \u201cReading Rooms.\u201d Recovery from a spinal injury inspired the beginnings of, for the point, what Christian sect, founded in the 19th century by Mary Baker Eddy, that believes illnesses can be cured through prayer?", "answer": "<b> Christian Science</b> (accept<b> Church of Christ, Scientist</b>; accept word forms, like<b> Christian Scientists</b>) (3) In a battle fought at this location, James Abercrombie decided not to deploy the full power of his artillery on Rattlesnake Hill, leading to a decisive defeat despite his superior numbers. This U.S. location was the site of a 1758 defensive victory for Louis-Joseph de Montcalm. Cannons from this location were transported to Boston in the Noble Train of Artillery after this location was captured by Benedict Arnold and Ethan Allen in a night raid. For the point, name this fort that once guarded a defensive strait near the south end of Lake Champlain. ANSWER: Fort<b> Ticonderoga</b> (or Fort<b> Carillon</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This composer arranged a campaign song that had been directed against James Blaine, \u201cThe Dodger,\u201das part of his<em> Old American Songs</em>. Eugene Goossens commissioned a piece by this man named for a Henry Wallace speech about the \u201ccentury\u201d of the title figure; that piece for brass and percussion was written during World War II. Martha Graham choreographed a work by this composer that features a setting of the Shaker hymn \u201cSimple Gifts.\u201d For the point, name this American composer of<em> Fanfare for</em> <em>the Common Man</em> and the ballet<em> Appalachian Spring</em>.", "answer": "Aaron<b> Copland</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Europeans used this commodity to trade with the 13 Factories in the Canton System. This commodity was brought to China when Spanish galleons traveled from Acapulco to Manila. Britain used this metal to trade for tea with China, before realizing that selling opium could reverse the flow of this commodity. Before traveling to Asia, this commodity was often mined in Bolivia via the mit\u00b4a system at Potos\u00b4\u0131. Chinese yuanbao ingots were made of gold and, for the point, what other precious metal?", "answer": "<b> silver</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 2007, 17 citizens of this country were killed in Nisour Square by private contractors. Three years earlier, the killing of four members of that private company, Blackwater, sparked the first Battle of Fallujah in this country. An invasion of this country was predicated on its attempt to buy yellowcake uranium from Niger. For the point, name this country that was named with Iran and North Korea in the\u201cAxis of Evil\u201d by George W. Bush in 2002, a year before the US invaded it to depose Saddam Hussein.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Iraq</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One of this leader\u2019s security chiefs was nicknamed the \u201cBloody Dwarf\u201d for his enjoyment of torturing political opponents. Leftist opposition to this leader was known as the United Opposition, which was co-organized by the author of<em> The Revolution Betrayed</em>. This man had Andrey Vyshinsky prosecute Lev Kamenev and Grigory Zinoviev in show trials, and had Nikolai Yezhov lead the Great Purge. For the point, name this leader of the Soviet Union through World War II.", "answer": "Joseph<b> Stalin</b> (or Josef<b> Dzhugashvili</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This empire was briefly interrupted by Sher Shah of the Sur Empire during the reign of Humayun. One ruler of this kingdom created his own religion called the Din-i Ilahi, encouraged learning at his House of Worship, and abolished the<em> jizya</em> tax on non-Muslims. This empire began with Ibrahim Lodi\u2019s loss at Panipat in 1526. Another ruler of this empire built a mausoleum for his wife Mumtaz. For the point, name this empire ruled by Babur, Akbar the Great, and Shah Jahan, who built the Taj Mahal.", "answer": "<b> Mughal</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "John de Vere commanded the vanguard at both this battle and, two years later, a quashed rebellion at Stoke Field. Nine days after this battle, William Caxton published Malory\u2019s<em> Le Morte D\u2019Arthur</em>, supposedly as commentary on this battle\u2019s most notable death. A full-on charge of roughly 1,000 knights was ordered by the loser of this battle, who had earlier served as Duke of Gloucester under his brother Edward IV. Richard III was killed at this battle, after which Henry VII was crowned. For the point, name this decisive 1485 battle of the Wars of the Roses.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Bosworth Field</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Winfield Scott was the last Presidential nominee of, for the point, what American political party whose leaders, like Henry Clay, opposed Andrew Jackson\u2019s Democrats in the 19th century?", "answer": "<b> Whig</b> Party", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city is home to an airport that is named in honor of Prime Minister Adolfo Suarez and is the busiest in its country. This city\u2019s Vicente Calder\u00b4on Stadium, which hosted its final game in 2017, included a stand of seating built over the M-30 highway that circles this city; a replacement stadium is being built a short drive from this city\u2019s aforementioned Barajas Airport. Nearly 200 people died in a 2004 terrorist attack on the train system of, for the point, what capital city of Spain?", "answer": "<b> Madrid</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The previous holder of this man\u2019s current position ended his tenure by inviting the Foo Fighters to play \u201cEverlong.\u201d This man, who was attacked by conservatives for his work as the host of the 2006 White House Correspondent\u2019s Dinner, led a 2010 \u201cMarch to Keep Fear Alive\u201d that was paired with a \u201cRally to Restore Sanity\u201d led by colleague Jon Stewart. David Letterman was succeeded by, for the point, what host of CBS\u2019s<em> Late Show</em> who once hosted a Comedy Central<em> Report</em> [re-pore]?", "answer": "Stephen<b> Colbert</b> [kohl-bayr]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a battle near Jindo Island, this weapon was deployed in a frontal attack after changing currents caused enemy ships to collide. These vessels, which were employed at the Battle of Myeongnyang [m\u2019yong-n\u2019yang] in the Imjin War, had a dragon\u2019s mouth mounted at their front to exhale either flames or a smokescreen. Yi Sun-sin re-designed this type of ship, which is named for the plates covering its top. For the point, name these large Korean warships whose shell-like armor earned a comparison to a reptile.", "answer": "<b> turtle ship</b>s (or<b> Geobukseon</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An architect who worked in this city designed its Carson Pirie Scott department store. Louis Sullivan was part of a school of architects named for this city, where<em> American Gothic</em> can be viewed. A brick structure in this city with art glass windows and a distinctive horizontal roof was built in the Prairie Style; that building is the Robie House in Hyde Park and was designed by Frank Lloyd Wright. For the point, name this city that was rebuilt after a \u201cGreat\u201d 1871 fire.", "answer": "<b> Chicago</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This work devotes two chapters to geographical distribution, including a brief discussion of boulders washed up on the Azores. Charles Lyell helped arrange the publication of this work, whose ideas were later applied to mankind in<em> The Descent of Man</em>. The study of finches and other creatures of the Galapagos Islands during a journey on the<em> Beagle</em> inspired, for the point, what 1859 work that introduced the idea of evolution by natural selection, written by Charles Darwin?", "answer": "On the<b> Origin of Species</b> by Means of Natural Selection Page 4", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A popular 18th century road named for these objects began in Philadelphia and worked through the backcountry to Augusta, Georgia. A specialized box was added to the back of these objects as made by the Studebaker family to provide storage and cooking utilities. The large Conestoga type of these vehicles was covered and could be caulked to cross rivers, and the \u201cchuck\u201d type served as a mobile kitchen. For the point, name these vehicles that transported American settlers and goods along the Oregon Trail prior to the expansion of railroads.", "answer": "<b> wagon</b>s (accept any specific type, such as Studebaker<b> wagon</b>; accept (Great)<b> Wagon</b> Road)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man may have issued the earliest mention of human rights on a cylinder, discovered in 1879, that has also led some biblical scholars to believe that this man ended the Babylonian Captivity. After defeating Croesus [kree-sus] of Lydia and the Median empire, this ruler established a new capital at Pasargadae [pass-AR-gah-dye]. This man\u2019s son, Cambyses II, carried on the Achaemenid line. For the point, name this founder of the Persian Empire.", "answer": "<b> Cyrus the Great</b> (or<b> Cyrus II</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The Spooner Amendment established a William Howard Taft-led government in this country, which was later granted independence via the Tydings-McDuffie Act. American involvement in this country was satirized in Mark Twain\u2019s \u201cA Defense of General Funston,\u201d a criticism of Frederick Funston\u2019s capture of Emilio Aguinaldo, this country\u2019s first President. For the point, name this Pacific island country where, in 1898, George Dewey destroyed the Spanish fleet in Manila Bay.", "answer": "Republic of the<b> Philippines</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A novel by this author begins with a man refusing to transport a group of Cubans into the US, but then agreeing to traffic some Chinese people instead. This author, who wrote about the smuggler Harry Morgan in<em> To Have and Have Not</em>, wrote a novel in which Anselmo is killed by flying shrapnel when he blows up a bridge during the Spanish Civil War. The demolitions expert Robert Jordan was created by, for the point, what American author of<em> For Whom the Bell Tolls</em>?", "answer": "Ernest<b> Hemingway</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "Gabriel Wells bought one of these works and broke it apart, selling its individual leaves. Guillaume-Fran\u00b8cois Debure\u2019s discovery of one of these in the Mazarin Library inspired an alternative name for these works, which are versions of the Vulgate. Only 49 copies of this work are known to have survived from the 1450s, when most of them were created in Mainz. The first major work to take advantage of the metal movable type was, for the point, what religious text named for the inventor of the printing press?", "answer": "<b> Gutenberg Bible</b> (accept descriptive answers, like<b> Bibles made by</b> Johannes<b> Gutenberg</b>; prompt on partial answers) Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A politician of this ethnicity named James Carroll twice served as acting Prime Minister. In World War I, Apirana Ngata supported a pioneer unit composed of these people, who developed the King Movement to unite on the North Island in the 19th century. Infighting among these people took place during the Musket Wars. Representatives of these indigenous peoples are guaranteed 7 electorates in a parliament at Wellington. William Hobson signed the Treaty of Waitangi with, for the point, what native peoples of New Zealand?", "answer": "<b> Maori</b> people (prompt on \u201cindigenous New Zealanders\u201d and \u201cAboriginal New Zealanders;\u201ddo not prompt on Aborigines)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In February 2017, this country\u2019s President joked that if he could, he would ban pineapple on pizza. The prime minister of this country resigned in 2016 after the release of the Panama Papers. This country\u2019s Pirate Party came in third place in October 2016 parliamentary elections, winning 10 seats in the Althing. Guoni Johannesson is president of, for the point, what Scandinavian country where the 2010 Eyjafjallajokull [AY-yah-f\u2019yat-la-yo-kuk] eruption cancelled flights out of Reykjavik [rake-ya-vik]?", "answer": "<b> Iceland</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In this city, tossing arrows at a statue of a divination god named Hubal was a religious rite practiced by this city\u2019s ruling Quraysh tribe in the 5th-century. The \u201cYear of the Elephant\u201d refers to a story where an invading army\u2019s leading elephant stopped outside the gates of this city; that elephant stopped due to the birth of a prophet from this city, whose move to neighboring Medina was known as the<em> hijra</em>. For the point, name this home of the Kaaba and birthplace of Muhammad.", "answer": "<b> Mecca</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This president fired his Attorney General, J. Howard McGrath, when McGrath refused to cooperate with a corruption investigation. Congress weakened labor unions by overriding this man\u2019s veto of the Taft-Hartley Act. This president announced Executive Order 9961, which integrated the armed forces, as part of his Fair Deal. For the point, name this man who defeated Thomas Dewey to maintain the presidency in 1948, having first gained the office after FDR\u2019s death.", "answer": "Harry S<b> Truman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A dictator in this nation once bathed in dolphin blood and changed currency to denominations of 45 and 90 units. A leader of this country implemented the order, \u201cwhen the army shoots, it shoots to hit,\u201dduring its 8888 Uprising. Ne Win was deposed in this country, where a national junta put down protests during UN Secretary General U Thant\u2019s funeral. Buddhists are persecuting Rohingya Muslims in, for the point, what country where Aung San Suu Kyi [chee] is state counsellor?", "answer": "Republic of the Union of<b> Myanmar</b> (accept<b> Burma</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 2013, a woman was arrested in Lens [lehn] for defacing this painting by writing \u201cAE911\u201d in black marker. This painting is an allegory of the July Revolution, which rocked Paris for three days in 1830, and shows a figure in a yellow dress and Phrygian cap stepping over several bodies. For the point, name this Eug`ene Delacroix [oo-zhen de-la-kwah] masterpiece whose title figure waves the French tricolor.", "answer": "<b> Liberty Leading the People</b> (or La<b> Libert\u00b4e guidant le peuple</b>; accept translations like <b>Liberty Guiding the People</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The losing side in this battle used forts supposedly named for its commander\u2019s mistresses, including\u201cClaudine\u201d and \u201cGabrielle.\u201d This battle was set up three months prior by the losing side\u2019s Operation Castor, a reinforcement by airdrop. During this two-month-long siege, Charles Piroth committed suicide after his forces were surrounded by artillery pieces hidden in the mountains. For the point, name this 1954 victory for Vo Nguyen Giap that led to French withdrawal from Vietnam.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Dien Bien Phu</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In one of these locations, Laboratory Number Seven is the site of phonoscopy research that analyzes voice patterns in encrypted telephone calls. A resident of one of these locations sews bread from his morning meal into his mattress for safekeeping. Lev Rubin is a resident of one of these locations in the novel<em> The First Circle</em>. Alexander Solzhenitsyn\u2019s novel<em> One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich</em> is set in, for the point, what type of location where Soviet dissidents were detained, often in Siberia?", "answer": "<b> gulag</b>s (accept Soviet<b> prison</b>s) Page 7", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "Two of this man\u2019s three formulations of his most famous concept are named after \u201cUniversal Law\u201dand \u201cAutonomy.\u201d This philosopher hypothesized that two constitutional republics will never go to war with each other, an idea described as \u201cPerpetual Peace.\u201d This man popularized the distinction between <em>a priori</em> and<em> a posteriori</em> statements in his 1781<em> Critique of Pure Reason</em>. The categorical imperative was described by, for the point, what 18th-century German Enlightenment philosopher?", "answer": "Immanuel<b> Kant</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "John Frederick I of Saxony and Philip I of Hesse led a league against this man, but were beaten by him at the Battle of Muhlberg. Francis I also fought this leader in the Italian Wars, but was beaten at Pavia. Due to the Protestant Reformation and the Schmalkaldic League, this Emperor promulgated the doctrine of<em> Cuius Regio, Eius Religio</em> with the Peace of Augsburg. For the point, name this Holy Roman Emperor who called the Diet of Worms [vohms] against Martin Luther.", "answer": "<b> Charles V</b>, Holy Roman Emperor (accept<b> Charles I of Spain</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A monopoly over production of these items was struck down in a suit brought by Fleer and Donruss against Topps. In 2013, Bill Mastro confessed to trimming one of these objects that had previously been owned by Wayne Gretzky; that object features Honus Wagner and was originally distributed in cigarette packs. For the point, name these collectible items, one of which erroneously features George W. Bush photoshopped in the stands behind Derek Jeter, the shortstop for the Yankees.", "answer": "baseball<b> trading cards</b> (or<b> baseball cards</b>; accept more generic answers, like sports<b> trading cards</b>; prompt on (sports) cards) Page 8", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Ricardo Rossello governs this unincorporated territory, where the potential failure of the Guajataca [gwa-ha-ta-ka] Dam in this territory prompted a mass evacuation of over 70,000 people here in 2017. For the point, name this U.S. territory with capital at San Juan that was devastated by Hurricane Maria.", "answer": "<b> Puerto Rico</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this event, the 1201 overflow alarm was correctly ignored. A day after celebrating the end of this event onboard the USS<em> Hornet</em>, President Nixon announced his namesake doctrine at a press conference in Guam. During this event, which was followed by three weeks of quarantine in Houston, Michael Collins remained in the Command Module while the<em> Eagle</em> landed in the Sea of Tranquility. For the point, name this 1969 mission in which Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong became the first men to walk on the moon.", "answer": "<b> Apollo 11</b> (accept descriptions of the<b> first Moon landing</b> before \u201cmission\u201d is read, prompting on such descriptions after; prompt on Apollo)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This empire expanded into Wagadou after the slave Sakoura seized power, but Sakoura was murdered and control quickly reverted back to the Kolonkan line. Architectural wonders from this empire include as-Saheli\u2019s Djinguereber Mosque and Djenne\u2019s Great Mosque. This empire was supplanted by the Songhai, and its most famous ruler legendarily devalued gold along the Mediterranean during his lavish hajj to Mecca. For the point, name this west African empire that was ruled by Mansa Musa.", "answer": "<b> Mali</b> Empire (or<b> Manden</b> Kurufaba)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In 1923, after people from this country were accused of killing Enrico Tellini, Italy bombarded one of its islands. Italy backed out of the Paris Peace Conference after learning that this country was promised Smyrna, which this country was occupying. Benito Mussolini invaded Albania before failing in his 1940 invasion of this country, whose Metaxas Line fell to the Germans the next year. The Corfu Incident enraged, for the point, what country that was occupied by the Nazis after the fall of Athens?", "answer": "<b> Greece</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this country, the city of Chan Chan was the base of power of the Chimu culture, who occupied a similar region as the earlier Moche [mo-chay] culture. A monkey with a spiraling tail is among the line-figures constructed in this modern country by the Nazca people. A civilization based in what is now this country was legendarily founded by Manco Capac, who established the city of Cusco. For the point, name this country, the base of power of the Inca civilization in South America.", "answer": "<b> Peru</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A Supreme Court case dealing with this concept is named for Richard Quirin, one of eight people who were planning acts of sabotage in Operation Pastorius. Access to this concept was upheld in an 1866 case that invalidated the conviction of Lambdin Milligan. The case<em> Ex Parte Merriman</em> ruled that President Lincoln\u2019s suspension of this right was unconstitutional. For the point, name this legal writ in which the legality of a person\u2019s imprisonment is challenged, known by a Latin phrase translating to \u201cbring forth the body.\u201d", "answer": "writ of<b> habeas corpus</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "When this war broke out, one side warned the USS<em> Vicksburg</em> and other neutral ships in Chemulpo Bay that an attack would take place the next day. General Kuropatkin lost 90,000 men and was forced to retreat from the largest battle of this war, Mukden. The Baltic Fleet was redeployed to join this conflict and relieve Port Arthur, only to be annihilated at the Battle of Tsushima Straits. For the point, name this 1904-1905 war in which an Asian power decisively defeated Tsar Nicholas II\u2019s forces.", "answer": "<b> Russo-Japanese</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man convinced Goldman Sachs to invest 60 million dollars in Chinese gold farms on World of Warcraft, an experience he claims taught him how to organize supporters over the Internet. This man was accused of leaking news to Mike Cernovich in an attempt to oust rival H.R. McMaster, who removed this man from the National Security Council in April 2017. After the Unite the Right Rally in Charlottesville and criticism of his white supremacist opinions, this man resigned from the Trump administration. For the point, name this former White House Chief Strategist and current chairman of Breitbart News.", "answer": "Steve<b> Bannon</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "A section of this river flowing through Ojinaga [oh-hee-naga] has been called \u201cThe Forgotten River\u201ddue to overuse and drought. A shift in this river caused the creation of Cordova Island, leading to the Chamizal border dispute and the near-assassination of two presidents in 1909. The question of whether to use the Nueces [noo-ays-ace] River or this river to determine a border led to a war that ended with the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. For the point, name this river on the US-Mexico border.", "answer": "Rio<b> Grande</b> (or Rio<b> Bravo</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A law forbidding this practice was central to the 1982 court case<em> Engblom v. Carey</em>, which arose after striking employees were removed from company housing. Several amendments to the Mutiny Act legalized this practice in the American colonies, as did the fourth of the Intolerable Acts. This practice, which was implemented due to a lack of lodging facilities beginning in the French and Indian War, is outlawed by the Third Amendment. For the point, name this practice of forcibly housing troops in private residences.", "answer": "<b> quartering</b> (accept elaborations, like<b> quartering</b> National Guard troops; prompt on descriptive answers before the final sentence)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these pieces premiered with lyrics satirizing its country\u2019s loss in the Seven Weeks War. This musical genre was introduced to England by Almack\u2019s social clubs. Maurice Ravel used two Schubert collections of these works for his own \u201cnoble and sentimental\u201d works, and denied that World War I influenced a piece of his named for this dance that depicted an imperial ballroom circa 1855. \u201cTales from the Vienna Woods\u201d and \u201cThe Blue Danube\u201d are examples of, for the point, what dance in three-quarter time whose \u201cKing\u201d was Johann Strauss Jr.?", "answer": "<b> waltz</b>es (or La<b> Valse</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The source of this river is often incorrectly cited as Lake Tear of the Clouds. The natural widening of this river, known as the Tappan Zee, tricked its namesake into thinking he\u2019d found the Northwest Passage, an idea he gave up on after reaching Troy. A historic railroad bridge converted into a footbridge over this river runs from Poughkeepsie to Highland. For the point, name this river that originates in the Adirondacks, forms the border between New York and New Jersey, and shares its name with the Canadian bay where its namesake was abandoned in 1611.", "answer": "<b> Hudson</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "During testimony in this case, former acting Secretary of State Levi Lincoln controversially requested time to consider whether he should answer any questions. This case was prompted by a writ of mandamus filed by one of the \u201cMidnight Judges,\u201d who had been appointed, in accordance with the Judiciary Act of 1801, at the very end of John Adams\u2019s presidency. For the point, name this 1803 case in which Chief Justice John Marshall established the principle of judicial review.", "answer": "<b> Marbury v. Madison</b> (accept in either order; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In that work, this man claims \u201che who destroys a good book kills reason itself.\u201d In another work by this author of<em> Areopagitica</em>, Mulciber is the principle architect of the city of Pandemonium, which is ruled by a character who claims that it is \u201cBetter to reign in Hell, than serve in Heaven.\u201d For the point, name this English author who looked to \u201cjustify the ways of God to man\u201d in<em> Paradise Lost</em>.", "answer": "John<b> Milton</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s country lost the Aozou Strip in the Toyota War against Chad. This leader, who was protected by the all-female Amazonian Guard, claimed responsibility for the 1988 Lockerbie bombings. This man detailed his Third International Theory in the<em> Green Book</em> shortly before taking the title\u201cBrotherly Leader and Guide of the Revolution.\u201d In 2011, this leader was killed near his hometown of Sirte during the Arab Spring. For the point, name this longtime dictator of Libya.", "answer": "Muammar<b> Gaddafi</b> (or<b> Qaddafi</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "John Pershing nicknamed this man \u201cbandito\u201d after he killed Mexican rebel leader Julio C\u00b4ardenas. This man, who was investigated by reporter Drew Pearson, beat Bernard Montgomery in the Race to Messina. Under Douglas MacArthur, this man led cavalry to suppress the Bonus Army. Before D-Day, this general led a phantom army to confuse German forces, and he directed the relief of the 101st Airborne during the Battle of the Bulge. For the point, name this American general who controversially slapped a soldier suffering from shell shock.", "answer": "George<b> Patton</b> Page 12", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This organization\u2019s membership boomed after they successfully striked against Jay Gould\u2019s Wabash Railroad. Many members of this organization participated in the 1885 Rock Springs Massacre of Chinese immigrants, though authorities could not link this group to the crime. This organization, which was founded as a secret \u201cNoble and Holy Order\u201d by Uriah Stephens, suffered a decline in popularity after it was blamed for the Haymarket Square Riot. For the point, name this briefly-powerful labor group once led by Terence Powderly.", "answer": "Noble and Holy Order of the<b> Knights of Labor</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1726, a marauding group of these people led by Hemperla were executed in the state of Hesse-Darmstadt. The 1530 Egyptians Act in England targeted these individuals. This group\u2019s flag features a 16-spoked wheel, a reference to their origins in northern India. These nomadic people often moved in caravans, leading many subgroups to be known as travellers. For the point, name this oft-persecuted, dispersed ethnic group that was marked by a brown triangle and murdered in the Porajmos by the Nazis.", "answer": "<b> Roma</b>ni (accept<b> Gypsy</b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man waged a decade-long campaign against the Ikko-Ikki that culminated in the destruction of Ishiyama Hongan-Ji. This man first rose to prominence when he ambushed an Imagawa army ten times the size of his own. This leader beat his rival Takeda at the Battle of Nagashino, using guns to great effect. After being betrayed by Akechi Mitsuhide, this leader committed suicide at Honno-ji. For the point, name this first of the Three Great Unifiers of Japan, an ally of Tokugawa Ieyasu and Toyotomi Hideyoshi.", "answer": "<b> Oda</b> Nobunaga", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Only four men survived an expedition intending to explore this U.S. state, including the chronicler Alvar Cabeza de Vaca. The Narvaez Expedition was formed in 1527 to explore this state. An explorer of this state landed at Charlotte Harbor on the Peace River north of Fort Myers as part of his quest to find the Fountain of Youth. Ponce de Leon led two voyages exploring, for the point, what state where the Spanish established colonies at St. Augustine and Pensacola?", "answer": "<b> Florida</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An emerald one of these figures has three sets of gold robes that are replaced by a current monarch at the end of each season. A<em> daibatsu</em> represents a giant sculpture of these figures, two of which were destroyed by the Taliban in Bamyan in 2001. The 9th-century temple of Borobodur on Java in Indonesia contains over 500 statues of these entities, which are often worshipped in Southeast Asia. For the point, name these figures that represent the founder of a religion with Mahayana and Theravada branches.", "answer": "<b> Buddha</b>s (accept elaborations, like \u201csculptures of the<b> Buddha</b>\u201d)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {"question": "These people allied with the Carthaginians against a Phocaean [fo-KAY-un] force at the Battle of Alalia. A league of these people consisted of twelve cities, including Clusium. These people, who called themselves the Rasenna, were attacked by invading Gauls at the Battle of Melpum and lost considerable control over the Po Valley. For the point, name this ethnic group located around the Tyrrhenian Sea that, after it lost its city of Veii, assimilated into the Roman Republic.", "answer": "<b> Etruscan</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}